<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Armies proposalls to the Parliament of the common-wealth of England, Scotland and Ireland</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25842</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23340</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12067345</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12067345</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53399</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25842)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53399)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 49:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Armies proposalls to the Parliament of the common-wealth of England, Scotland and Ireland</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
                  <author>Ireland. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53399:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53399:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Armies Propoſalls TO THE PARLIAMENT OF THE Common-wealth of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold in Fleet-ſtreet, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:53399:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53399:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Supream Authority OF THESE NATIONS, THE PARLIAMENT OF THE <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Humble Petitions and Propoſals of the Officers under the Command of the Right Honorable the Lord <hi>Lambert,</hi> in the late Northern expedition.</head>
            <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT whereas we with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who deſire to fear the Lord in theſe Nations (though by our provocations we are ripe for deſtruction) have been again ſaved by the Lord, and have had a late view of his appearances as of old, in the beholding of whoſe gracious footſteps as we cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53399:3"/>ſo our ſouls tremble leaſt the fruit and birth of all (which the Lord may expect, and his people long earneſtly for) become abortive now in the day of our deliverance; we do therefore preſent unto your Honors conſideration, theſe enſuing Propoſals which we do humbly lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That the Humble Petition and Addreſs of the General Counſel of Officers at <hi>Wallingford</hi>-houſe to the Parliament, which was ſo unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly and cheerfully agreed unto, and approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of in a day of our greateſt confuſions, may not be laid aſleep, but may have freſh life given unto it; It being (upon further and cleerer grounds) ſtill upon our hearts as the beſt and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expedient, yet offered (notwithſtanding many aſſayes) to a happy and durable ſettlement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a fixed and firm fence and boundary (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God) for the ſecuring of the Civil and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Liberties, which the Spirit of the Nation is unwearied in travil, not onely to invade, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every opportunity (as we we have often ſeen, and lately had a cleer evidence of) is ready to attempt the ruin and deſtruction of the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That whereas God having given a Spirit to the Army ſixed and faithful to the intereſt of his people, and our good old cauſe, when many who had been friends, were either Apoſtates, Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants or Newters, joyning with the old Enemy, leaving the Parliament and Army, and their few active friends ſingly to conflict with their late difficulties, and having now no ſuch hopeful way,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53399:3"/>like to prevail, and ruin, and fruſtrate what we have ſo long contended for, as by working divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the Army, making breaches, begetting miſunderſtandings, and diſſolving its Union (wherein, under God, it's ſtrength lies) We do therefore as the moſt effectual means, for the maintaining of the Diſcipline and conduct there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and preſerving its Union inviolable, humbly Propoſe, That his Excellency the Lord <hi>Fleetwood</hi> may be ſettled Commander in chief of the Armies, his Commiſſion expiring within a few months; That the Lord <hi>Lambert</hi> be the General Officer, and chief Commander of the Army next under him: Alſo that General <hi>Desbrough</hi> be the chief Officer of the horſe under them, and that Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Monck</hi> be the chief Officer of the Infantry, they being perſons, under whoſe conduct, cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and fidelity, we have had eminent ſucceſs, victories and deliverances in the days of great ſtraits, and have been ſignally bleſt and owned by the Lord, to whom, and not to man be the honor of all.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That having had very ſad experiences of a grand Apoſtatizing and Newteral Spirit gone through the Nations, and amongſt many of thoſe who were intruſted for the ſafety thereof, very few acting or appearing in ſeveral Counties, for the preventing the Plots, and ſuppreſſing the powers of the enemy in their late Rebellious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; and many others not onely faultering, but falling in with them, were by a total ruin, was threatned, and had been effected, had not the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53399:4"/>Lord in mercy prevented it. We therefore hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Propoſe, that there may be a diligent inquiry in all parts by faithful men, imployed to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, what intruſted Perſons have been guilty of any contrivance, or acted againſt the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths intereſt, and that they may be proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt accordingly; and likewiſe what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons upon wicked purpoſes have been Newteral in ſuch a diſtracted day, when their aſſiſtance accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their imployments and truſt, would have been no leſs uſeful then ſeaſonable; and that all ſuch may be removed from their places and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, Civil and Military, and that ſuch who on the contrary have in this juncture of your diſcompoſed affairs, declared their owning of this intereſt, either in the County Troops, Militia, Volanteers, or otherways, may be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon as friends, incouraged, ſatisfied, their Arrears protected from injuries, countenanced by you, and as they are capacitated, inveſted with authority in their ſeveral Countries.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That in the late Inſurrections, ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Corporations have not onely added, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betted, and countenanced the enemies deſigns, but alſo have made uſe of the Armes lodged with them, and themſelves appeared in the rebellion, willingly receiving the numerous affections of all engaged therein: Therefore we humbly propoſe, That ſuch Corporations may be diſcountinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and that you would be pleaſed to give your ſignal mark of disfavor againſt them; as alſo for the future, ſo to regulate Corporations, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53399:4"/>ſuch perſons well qualified according to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of a well conſtituted Common-wealth may be inveſted with the authority of Magiſtracy in every Town, that ſo the footſteps of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy may be raſed out.</p>
            <p n="5">V. We humbly offer, that all perſons whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, Magiſtrates, Miniſters, or others, who have openly, or ſecretly ſtirred up, or provoked the inhabitants of theſe Nations to war and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion againſt the Parliament, and particular to the late Inſurrections, which is too viſibly appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, many of them having not onely been abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but in their perſons appeared with inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and weapons of war (as ſome of us know) may be proceeded againſt, as you in your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments think fit.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
